I think I figured out a way to plan any
size of work with an agent. The existing
planning tools that I was using and
playing around with, even ones that I've
created, felt too constrained, too tied
to a single session. I felt like I
wasn't able to be ambitious enough. And
because of that, I was kind of
constraining the stuff I was building to
fit AI, which doesn't feel right. This
new approach doesn't have that limit.
You can plan enormous chunks of work and
it will orchestrate the planning over
multiple types of sessions. It knows
that you can't make your way cleanly to
the destination. You have to clear the
fog of war. It understands dependent
decisions and it even allows you to plan
in parallel. And the best thing about
this is this is based on software
fundamentals. This is based on the
fundamentals of planning work that I
learned when I was a real developer
before AI. And I've packaged this all up
into a skill that's available right now
on my skills repo called wayfinder. So
the way that I was planning work before
was really tied into a single session.
It's to do with the grill me or the
grill with doc skill that's in my skills
repo. That's still a super important
primitive, but it's really just tied
into a single session. Some work is
bigger than what you can fit into the
context window and especially the smart
zone of the context window of the agent.
And you know that going in. So you'll
often take time ahead of these AI agent
sessions to break it down into smaller
chunks. Say, "Oh, I'll just bite off
this little bit. I'll just bite off this
little bit." But then what you'll find
is, "Okay, I'm working towards planning
in this bit of grilling." And then you
reach a question that you can't answer
or you just find yourself lost in fog
and all the time you're managing the
smart zone. You're trying not to spend
too many tokens. This has been out there
for a while and people are freaking
loving this thing. it. One shot at a
prototype, it kept starting again and
again for months. I really hate the
phrase oneshotting, but I think what he
means is it really helped him out. John
here even built his own freaking harness
because he liked the wayfinder approach
so much. It's got this gorgeous little
star map on it that kind of lets you
take tasks as you go. So, it's been out
there for a little while and I'm finally
making the video that people want me to
make. What is Wfinder? How do you best
use it? Well, let's start by looking at
how big work typically gets planned. You
have a start point, a point where you
need to start from, a sort of vague
idea, not really how to get there, and
you're trying to get to some kind of
destination. You know vaguely where you
want to end up, but the steps between
are super foggy. You've no idea how to
get. This is true, by the way, in
engineering, but it's also true in many
walks of life where you're planning
something ambitious. And so, the first
thing you should probably do is have a
grilling session about it. get the AI to
interview you and figure out the sort of
basic premise of where you're going.
Now, for some work, that's sufficient
and you'll be able to get straight to
your destination, but for a lot of work,
that will still leave you in a lot of
fog. What you might find is based on
that initial grilling session, you need
to do more sessions. So, you might have
a prototyping session or you might have
another grilling session or it might
need to go off and do some research as
well. Conceptually, what we're looking
at here is a map. We are creating a map
of how we're getting to our destination.
This is why it's called wayfinder. We
are finding our way to the destination.
And each of these things on the map,
they are tickets. Each ticket requires
its own individual session with the
agent. So you might have a prototyping
session, a grilling session, and a
research session. And all of those
things are created and managed by
Wfinder. And just a note here, yeah,
this is just a single skill doing all
this. And it works with any coding
agent. On its map, Wfinder gives you a
frontier of tickets here. In other
words, the decisions that it knows about
so far. And it also keeps track of
everything that's in fog. So things that
are not quite able to be decided upon
yet because we haven't done the research
or we don't have a prototype to look at
or we haven't done enough conversation,
enough grilling. At some point all of
the fog will be resolved and then you'll
have finally made enough decisions to
finally get to your destination.
Wayfinder can not only manage the
research but it can also do tasks here
too. So, if you need to set up some
configuration or you need to go out and
talk to someone and actually go and run
an errand, then Wayfinder can figure
that out for you as well. In other
words, all of the complicated stuff that
you might need to do while you're
planning something big, Wayfinder
orchestrates it all for you. It keeps
track of everything that's been done and
it measures the fog of war for you.
Keeps track of all the frontier of
things you can decide right now. How
does it keep track of it? Well, it does
it in your issue tracker in my public
course video manager repo. Here are all
of the Wayfinder maps that I've done
recently. And you notice that if we look
at this one, there are this is the big
old map here. And underneath it are 12
subtasks or sub issues and these are the
decision tickets. So we can zoom down
here and we can understand all of the
decisions that have been made. As
decisions get made then obviously they
get resolved inside the ticket. So in
this one this is a sub issue close the
clips during publish race and we
resolved it with a discussion a couple
of weeks ago. That resolution also gets
written back up to the parent map. So if
we look back up here we can see that a
small version of that also gets written
in the map. And so Wayfinder is keeping
track of all the decisions that have
been made, all the prototypes that have
been created, all the tasks that have
been done. And by the way, even though
I'm using GitHub for this, my skills are
issue tracker agnostic. So you can use
it with any issue tracker you like. You
just need to do a little bit of
configuration via setup map skills. Use
it with linear, use it with Jira, use it
with literally whatever you like. The
very first thing you'll need to decide
when you kick off a new wayfinder
session is the destination. For
instance, in this one, I was adding a
command pallet with a bunch of new
actions into my application. And what I
ended up wanting was a buildable spec.
So, I wanted a specification for this
command K command pallet in the CVM
diagram window. So, I started it off
like this. I invoked the wayfinder skill
and then I gave it a description of what
I wanted. I would like the ability in
the CVM to add an icon picker. Not only
that, I want the ability to search other
diagrams. I want the ability to copy
things from the diagram and save them as
you know big old chunk of work. It went
through and explored the uh repo and it
invoked the grilling skill and it
grilled me about what I wanted. It first
asked me what done looks like whether I
wanted a spec and it recommended a spec.
That's good. And then it asked me a few
initial questions before then going and
creating some tickets and the first map
and it created the other tickets as sub
issues. So we kicked off with seven
tickets immediately. However, only three
of those tickets were takable right now.
So figure out where icon names come
from, component storage schema, and
pallet information architecture and grid
keyboard. I don't remember that one. And
so what I did was I then worked through
each of those tickets in a new session.
The way I did that was I just called
wayfinder on that ticket name. I did it
in a slightly fancier way where I
actually have a handoff skill that
automatically wrote me a prompt and
spawned a clawed sub agent. But what it
was essentially doing is just calling
the wayfinder skill on this map and on
the specific ticket wherever it was.
Yeah, here it is. Here's your ticket.
Uh, transpar lucid SVG geometry to path
builder and it just mentions the full
ticket name. So, this is how you work
through a wayfinder map. You do an
initial wayfinder prompt just to chart
the map and figure out the next ticket.
And then for each ticket, you say
Wfinder with the ticket URL. So, you use
Wfinder for both. both for charting the
map initially and then walking through
each ticket. As you can probably see
from this diagram, tickets can have
different types and there are four types
and these ticket types are actually
brought into the issue tracker
themselves. So we actually have
wayfinder research which is a ticket
type. Research tickets are where the
agent needs to go off and find some
information and bring it back and it
usually kicks it off immediately. So you
don't actually need to watch it. It does
it in a sub agent and then reports back.
Prototype tickets, which are the next
type here, create a prototype, which is
so unbelievably invaluable for really
seeing things come to life as you're
planning. I've done a whole extra video
on this on how important prototypes are,
and it reuses the prototype skill from
that video. Some folks look at Wayfinder
and they think, "God, that's a lot of
planning. Doesn't that look like
waterfall?" And the prototypes are the
way that you prevent it from becoming
waterfall. Huge amounts of lowfidelity
upfront planning. A prototype is a
highfidelity way to get feedback on what
you're actually building. And the fact
that Wfinder encourages you to build so
many prototypes means that the output is
unbelievably good. So, so far we got
research prototype. Obviously, there are
grilling ones as well. So, grilling
sessions and this is just where you need
a discussion over maybe an
implementation detail over a particular
aspect of the plan. And the final type
of tickets are tasks. These are things
that need to be done in the real world,
stuff that the agent can't quite do
itself or possibly sometimes the stuff
agent can do itself but is scheduled
behind other work. One really cool thing
about Wavefinder is the way that it
establishes blocking relationships
between tickets because some decisions
can only be made once other decisions
are made. And so what you end up with is
here we've got 14 out of 17 done on this
map. So, a lot of work done, but we've
still not built the skill that this
whole map is built around. And once
we've built the skill, then we actually
need to revisit some other stuff based
on how the skill works and how it
actually improves things. And so, what
you're doing a lot of the time when
you're working through a wayfinder map
is going, okay, I've resolved that
ticket. Let's see how this opens up new
tickets. What has the frontier moved to?
So, then once the map is complete, what
do you then go and do with it? Well,
this one because its detonation was a
speck, the wayfinder map is probably a
little bit too dense to create a spec.
So, what I like to do is create a spec
from the map. This was the spec that I
created from it. And you can see it's
basically the same setup as I've had
before. I literally just called to spec
on the wayfinder map and it pulled in
this enormous
document with basically all of the
decisions that have been pulled from the
wayfinder map into this uh GitHub issue.
The initial draft was actually too large
for GitHub's character limit. So
[laughter] that kind of tells you how
big it was. And from there I turned it
into tickets using my usual approach
which is to spec and then to tickets. In
other words, Wfinder fits in just in
exactly the same place that grill with
docs does in my usual approach. So
instead of doing grill with docs and
then doing to spec and to tickets,
you're spending a lot more time in
wavefinder creating this enormous map
and then taking that map, turning it to
spec, turning it to tickets, and then
implementing each ticket and then
running code review at the end. The
really cool thing about the Wfinder
setup is that the specs that it creates
are so dense and they all link back to
the original decision tickets. So you
can actually go and the agent can go and
view the primary source if it's confused
about anything. That was always a kind
of uh weakness with Grill with Docs,
which is that you were really relying on
the spec to be the source of truth, but
the spec is always just a summary of
what was actually said in the meeting.
Whereas now with Wfinder, you've
actually got access to that primary
source, which is amazing. So that is
Wfinder. It's a way of mapping huge
chunks of work by planning things out
really in detail ahead of time. It can
handle prototyping, can handle research,
can handle arbitrary tasks, can handle
discussions, too. Let's jump into an FAQ
now of frequently asked questions that I
get when people ask me about Wayfinder.
The first one is this is way too much
process. uh this way too heavy for the
kind of work that I do when should I
actually use it? Well, the answer to
this is if you think the work that
you're doing can be completable and
plannable in a single session, then plan
it in a single session. If you kind of
already know the way to your
destination, then there's no need to use
Wfinder because you can just path your
way there in a single session and just
figure it out. Wayfinder is for the
cases where you have the fog of war.
You'll no idea quite where to go and you
just need to start and then see where
you get to. By the way, I've actually
been using Wayfinder for non-coding
tasks. So, I've been meaning to put up a
garden office in my garden and uh I've
been using Wayfinder for that. So, it's
uh commissioning a site survey, uh
figuring out all that stuff, figuring
out who to contact, doing all the
research, finding the different firms
that could build it. It's awesome.
Another response people have to Wfinder
is, "This is STD. This is spec driven
development, and I don't want to do
spectrum development. I don't want to
spend all this time putting together a
spec. This seems bananas." Well, the way
I think of specs is really just a
destination for a multiseession piece of
work. In other words, we have a huge
task down here, let's say task number
four that we're trying to schedule over
multiple agent sessions because it's
just too big. And what we want to do is
we need a spec so that we can when we
get to the end figure out where we were
going. That's all a spec is in this
context. It's just a destination
document to handle this multi-session
work. And then each session is done in
an implementation ticket. Also, this is
people get confused when they first use
Wfinder because they go, "Right, it's
creating some tickets. Aren't we
supposed to do the tickets later? These
are kind of implementation tickets
versus decision tickets." So, in
Wfinder, you have decision tickets.
These are implementation tickets. So,
the difference between my approach and
most other approaches is that people
when they get to the end of this, they
will keep that spec around somewhere.
For me, I close the issue containing the
spec and the spec is gone. It's gone
from my repository. I rarely if ever
refer to it again. Once the spec is
present in the code, then you can just
delete the spec. Whereas people who do
specdriven development go back to the
spec and edit it and modify it. There
are lots of approaches to spectrum
development, so I'm probably annoying
someone with that. But what I'm
essentially trying to say is that these
specs are non-persistent. So with that
folks, I recommend you go off and you
chart your own awesome foggy idea. I
have found wayfinder just so liberating
in that it just lets me get started and
it handles all of that difficult
decision for me. I've been using it to
plan courses, been using it to do
engineering work, been using it to build
a garden office. It is just awesome. And
the cool thing about it is that the
destination is totally up to you.
Whether you want it to create a spec
that you then run through an AFK agent,
which is what I do, or if you just want
to it to implement the work for you in
uh tasks, then it totally can. There is
no more fun feeling than starting a new
wayfinder session and knowing that
you're going to see something awesome,
but not quite knowing how you're going
to get there. If you're into this stuff
and if you want to keep up with my
skills, then you should check out this
seven lesson free course that I've put
out on AI skills for real engineers,
which is on my AI hero site. I'll add
the link below. This lets you build up a
repeatable workflow that you can ship
great work and it's all built on solid
software fundamentals. Thanks so much
for hanging out. It is always fun
filming these sessions and I'm so glad
that people are enjoying Wayfinder so
much. So, cheers pals. I will see you in
the next